<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://taufik-my.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://taufik-my.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-08-15T08:17:36+00:00</updated><id>https://taufik-my.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Welcome to Taufik&apos;s personal website :) </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Scholarship Application Story Epilogue: The Dilemma and The Decision</title><link href="https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/scholarship-epiloge/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scholarship Application Story Epilogue: The Dilemma and The Decision"/><published>2023-07-08T06:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-08T06:57:00+00:00</updated><id>https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/scholarship-epiloge</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/scholarship-epiloge/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-dilemma">The Dilemma</h2> <p>How would you feel if you received two prestigious scholarships simultaneously? You would be overjoyed, right? Yes, I was ecstatic, speechless, and couldn’t believe that I had received both the Global Korea Scholarship and Monbukagakusho Japan. However, the excitement only lasted for about three days before three months of confusion hit me hard. I never expected to experience something similar to what Maudy Ayunda (whom I admire, by the way, as Stanford and Harvard both accepted her) had gone through. But personally, I believe my situation was even more complicated – I had to choose between two countries, two different majors, two universities, and two scholarship programs. My tendency to overthink and my past experience of making a poor decision made it difficult for me to decide.</p> <p>The decision-making process was complicated by other factors. To be honest, I had been dreaming of studying abroad through the GSEP Tokyo Tech since I was in the 12th grade. Japan was, and still is, my dream country to study in Asia (please note that this doesn’t mean I don’t want to study in Korea). Having lived in Tokyo for about a month, I missed the country, even until now. So why didn’t I simply choose Japan? It’s because my desire to study computer science remained strong, even though the transdisciplinary major that I would learn at Tokyo Tech was also very interesting. So, until now, there was a significant tie between the country and the major. Another factor was my financial situation. I had promised myself not to ask my parents for money from the process of applying to both scholarships until I go abroad to study. I knew that I needed money for both GKS and MEXT to survive for the first month in Korea or Japan, so I was researching and calculating everything. Now, there were three major problems: the country, the major, and money.</p> <h2 id="the-decision">The Decision</h2> <p>Why did I choose KAIST in the end? Let’s break down the problems and explain the reasons.</p> <ol> <li> <p>Regarding the <strong>country</strong>, after leading a nomadic life and visiting several countries in Asia, I felt like they were all somewhat similar, even though they’re actually not. I realized that I am the kind of person who doesn’t really care about the place where I’m going to live. It’s not as simple as it sounds, but I felt that since my purpose of living in that country is to STUDY, the thing that we’re going to learn in college is more important than the country itself.</p> </li> <li> <p>Regarding the <strong>major</strong>, I remembered that when I wrote my essay for the GSEP application, I still mentioned ‘computer stuff’ even though I knew that at Tokyo Tech I would major in transdisciplinary science and engineering (TSE). Both majors are very fascinating, but I felt that I was more into computer science. However, my overthinking made me constantly question whether I would be more successful if I majored in TSE, or if computer science was actually not for me. What I did was conduct more research and ask for the experiences of seniors who are studying at Tokyo Tech and KAIST. I discovered that at KAIST we don’t need to declare our major in the freshman year, and there’s a major similar to TSE too. I liked this kind of flexibility at KAIST and, fortunately, most of the courses in all of the departments are in English, so if I wanted to change my major, I could still do it if I chose KAIST. At KAIST, I could also learn courses from not just one major (we can do a double major or minor in another major). I was interested in this program, and if my brain could handle it, which I hope it can, I really wanted to learn both computer science and business and technology management.</p> </li> <li> <p>Regarding <strong>money</strong>, after asking the seniors, I found out that to survive for the first month in Korea I would need about 2 – 4 million IDR, because GKS provides a settlement allowance too, and they said that the first monthly allowance would be transferred within 2 – 3 weeks after arriving in Korea, which turned out to be true. For Japan, the university itself suggested that I bring at least 150,000 JPY, which was too much for me to handle, but my senior suggested that I bring at least 60,000 JPY – 100,000 JPY (about 8 – 12 million IDR), which was also a lot for me. The school also told me that the first monthly stipend would be given approximately 1.5 months after arriving in Japan. Even though there were people (Thank you so much to Rudi and Hendra) who could help me with this money problem no matter whether I chose Japan or Korea, I didn’t want to be a significant burden for others. So, because of this factor, I chose the one which was ‘easier’ for me financially.</p> </li> </ol> <p>Actually, there were other reasons too, but those three that I mentioned above were very significant factors that led me to choose KAIST. In this post, I don’t want to compare one to another because the opportunities that I got were too good for me and successfully put me in a sweet-sour dilemma, plus it gave me a severe headache for two days in a row.</p> <p>This dilemma not only taught me a lot about decision-making but also about the importance of respecting other people’s decisions because there will be reasons that we don’t know behind their decisions. We also don’t know how hard it is for someone to decide and how complicated it is. Therefore, never judge other people’s decisions if we know nothing!</p> <p>This story is the end of the scholarship application story series. I hope we can learn something from these stories. See you in the next post.</p> <p>200419 – Under the rain and wanting to smell the petrichor but too lazy to go outside~</p> <p><strong>-written on April 19, 2020-</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="slice of life"/><category term="scholarship"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Dilemma]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scholarship Application Story: Global Korea Scholarship for Undergraduate Degree 2020 (GKS/KGSP) Embassy Track 🇰🇷</title><link href="https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/gks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scholarship Application Story: Global Korea Scholarship for Undergraduate Degree 2020 (GKS/KGSP) Embassy Track 🇰🇷"/><published>2023-07-01T05:52:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-01T05:52:00+00:00</updated><id>https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/gks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/gks/"><![CDATA[<p>First and foremost, I’m not entirely sure what to write here because many people have already shared their experiences of receiving this scholarship. Nevertheless, here’s my story.</p> <h1 id="global-korea-scholarship-gks-in-a-nutshell">Global Korea Scholarship (GKS) in a nutshell</h1> <p>The GKS is a fully-funded scholarship program from the Republic of Korea government designed to attract international students to study in Korea. The scholarship is available for both undergraduate and graduate degree programs. I won’t delve into the details of the scholarship itself because you can find comprehensive guidelines on the <a href="https://www.studyinkorea.go.kr">Study in Korea</a> website. If you’re Indonesian, you can also find information on the <a href="https://overseas.mofa.go.kr/id-id/brd/m_2707/list.do">Embassy of the Republic of Korea in Indonesia’s website</a>. Happy reading!</p> <h1 id="a-little-background">A Little Background</h1> <p>I applied for this scholarship twice, first in 2018 for GKS 19 and then in 2019 for GKS 20. In my first attempt, I was placed on the <strong>waiting list</strong>, meaning that if someone dropped out or failed in the scholarship application process, I could join as a successful candidate. However, if you’re selected as a <strong>waiting list</strong> candidate, don’t get your hopes up too high because there’s a 99% chance you’re <strong>NOT</strong> going to make it. In this post, I’m just going to share my GKS 20 story because if I also talk about my GKS 19 application story, it would make for a very long post, and frankly, I’m not a great storyteller.</p> <h1 id="1st-round">1st Round</h1> <h2 id="document-screening">Document Screening</h2> <p>Honestly, for the GKS 20 application, I wasn’t as serious and ambitious to get this scholarship as I was for the GKS 19 application. I wasn’t really sure about my GSEP application because the quota for the scholarship was just <strong>for the 8 best students worldwide</strong>. Because of this, I convinced myself that I had to apply for other scholarships to increase my chances of going to college with a fully-funded scholarship.</p> <p>The other reasons why I applied were first, the quota for Indonesia increased from <strong>3 in GKS 19</strong> to <strong>5 in GKS 20</strong>, and second, I still had the documents from my GKS 19 application, so I didn’t spend any money on the application except for the shipping cost to send my documents to the Korean Embassy.</p> <p>For GKS 2020, I didn’t make significant improvements in my application. I just changed my essays (personal statement + study plan) and added my SAT Subject Score. For your information, I also attached my TOEFL iBT score and several certificates to support my application. You also need to <strong>officially translate and notarize all of your documents</strong>. Even though in my GKS 19 application I didn’t notarize my documents and just translated them because I didn’t have a lot of money for that, I still passed the document screening! Then, during a phone call, the embassy asked me to notarize my documents and bring them during the interview. <strong>THEREFORE</strong>, I highly recommend you to <strong>NOT ONLY translate your documents BUT ALSO NOTARIZE THEM</strong> from the beginning before sending them to the embassy!</p> <p><strong>My Tips for Document Screening:</strong> Arrange your documents as neatly and as well as possible! Don’t get too confused because of other people’s opinions on how to organize them! Just believe in yourself!</p> <h2 id="the-interview">The Interview</h2> <p>The embassy will announce the candidates who will be interviewed on their website and through an email to the interviewees. Here are the interview announcements for the GKS-U 2019 and 2020 in Indonesia. Every year in Indonesia, the number of people called for interviews is three times the quota of scholarship recipients. So for the GKS 20, because the quota was 5, the interviewees were 15 people, and for the GKS 19, because the quota was 3, the interviewees were 9 people.</p> <p>For GKS 2020, the interview was held on <strong>October 30, 2019</strong>. There were two batches, the morning batch, and the afternoon batch. My interview was in the afternoon batch. I was pretty relaxed and confident for the interview because I had experienced something similar before and I wasn’t overly concerned about the result. Once again, the most important thing for me is making new friends and gaining new experiences. For the GKS 2020, I didn’t have any incomplete documents, so the embassy didn’t ask me to bring anything to the interview. The good thing about the interview of the GKS Embassy track in Indonesia is that you’re going to get a bag of <em>Tous Les Jours</em> for free. For your information, I felt that the interview questions for GKS 2019 were more challenging than for GKS 2020. For GKS 2019, two other candidates and I were interviewed for about 1 hour - the longest interview period in the GKS history in Indonesia as the embassy staff said, but for GKS 2020, it was just about 10 minutes. It was a really short interview.</p> <p>The interview result came out on <strong>November 4, 2019</strong> - the deadline for the embassy to forward the successful candidate’s documents to the NIIED. It was in the morning when I was doing a little research on my laptop, then there’s an email from the Korean Embassy that I passed the interview round; I was so excited because I passed, no more being on the waiting list, and actually, if you pass this step, your chance to get the scholarship is like 90%.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gks-19-itv-rslt?w=1423&amp;h=&amp;zoom=2-480.webp 480w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gks-19-itv-rslt?w=1423&amp;h=&amp;zoom=2-800.webp 800w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gks-19-itv-rslt?w=1423&amp;h=&amp;zoom=2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gks-19-itv-rslt.png?w=1423&amp;h=&amp;zoom=2" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gks-20-itv-rslt?w=1410&amp;h=&amp;zoom=2-480.webp 480w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gks-20-itv-rslt?w=1410&amp;h=&amp;zoom=2-800.webp 800w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gks-20-itv-rslt?w=1410&amp;h=&amp;zoom=2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gks-20-itv-rslt.png?w=1410&amp;h=&amp;zoom=2" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The invitation emails from the embassy. </div> <p><strong>My Tips for Interview:</strong> Dress well, prepare for the expected questions (you can google them), don’t be nervous and stay calm, and answer the questions briefly. Never memorize your answers! Just answer the questions naturally :)</p> <h1 id="2nd-round">2nd Round</h1> <h2 id="the-niied-selection">The NIIED Selection</h2> <p>After passing the 1st round, you just need to wait for another announcement, which is the second round result selection from the NIIED. In this period, I was also waiting for my GSEP results. The 2nd round result was announced on the www.studyinkorea.go.kr, they were late to announce the result (it was expected to be announced on November 18, but in reality, the announcement was on <strong>November 22</strong>), but anyway I passed the 2nd round selection, and it was such a relief.</p> <p>Passing this round meant that I had to do a medical check-up because we need to send it along with our passport copy to the NIIED. It was a dilemma for me because doing a medical check-up is kind of expensive and on the other hand, I am still waiting for my GSEP results to arrive at my home (you need to read my post about my GSEP application story because everything is connected). But in the end, I did the medical check-up and after that, I got the announcement that I got the scholarship for the GSEP. It was the biggest dilemma in my life so far.</p> <p>It was November 30, after thinking about what I should choose for about 3 days, I decided to send a confirmation letter to the GSEP admission committee, and send a resignation letter to the NIIED and the Korean Embassy. <strong>I did that because I hoped I could save the GKS 20 waiting lists to replace my position</strong>. But the dilemma was not over because after that the Embassy called me asking whether I was sure about my decision or not, and they said that I couldn’t save the waiting lists, it was really heartbreaking for me 😭, so in the end, I was still continuing the process of GKS 20 to wait for the university admission results.</p> <h1 id="3rd-round">3rd Round</h1> <h2 id="university-admission-results">University Admission Results</h2> <p>While waiting for the university admission results, I was really stressed because of everything, that’s why I did A LOT of research, consulted with the people I trust to ask about their opinions regarding which path should I choose? Japan or Korea? Major A or Major B? and many more. Trust me, getting two prestigious scholarships is not as exciting as you thought! It was really depressing, at least for an overthinking person like me. And because of this, I also got cyberbullied, I didn’t know how since I never posted anything on my social media, but anyway I didn’t care. Honestly, it takes a lot of consideration for me to start writing this story, because I’d been afraid that there will be a lot of people who will hate and bully me because of my decision, but yeah here I am :’).</p> <p>Okay, let’s continue to the main topic here haha. I chose <strong>KAIST, SNU, and KU</strong> in my GKS 20 application. The announcement was scheduled for <strong>December 19, 2019</strong>, but SNU sent an email before that they would announce the result on December 20. To be honest, I was pretty confident to get into SNU and KU because based on the history, there weren’t Indonesian applicants who got rejected from those universities, BUT for KAIST, I knew it was kind of hard to get into because based on the result of the last couple years, there were just 4-5 people who chose KAIST as their university through the GKS program, means that the acceptance rate to KAIST is pretty low too. But here are my results:</p> <ul> <li> <ul> <li><strong>KAIST - <span style="color:blue">Accepted</span></strong></li> </ul> <p><img src="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/kaist.jpg?w=426&amp;h=602" alt="KAIST"/></p> </li> <li> <ul> <li><strong>Seoul National University - <span style="color:red">Rejected</span></strong></li> </ul> </li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/snu-rslt?w=968&amp;h=470-480.webp 480w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/snu-rslt?w=968&amp;h=470-800.webp 800w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/snu-rslt?w=968&amp;h=470-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/snu-rslt.png?w=968&amp;h=470" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <ul> <li><strong>Korea University (KU) - <span style="color:blue">Accepted</span></strong></li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/ku-result?w=1038&amp;h=504-480.webp 480w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/ku-result?w=1038&amp;h=504-800.webp 800w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/ku-result?w=1038&amp;h=504-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/ku-result.png?w=1038&amp;h=504" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>I was kind of shocked with my results though because KAIST accepted me but SNU rejected me, it’s kind of out of my expectation and made my dilemma more complicated. In the end, I chose KAIST because obviously it was my first choice and the courses at KAIST are taught in English - since I don’t want to study my major in Korean. From that time, the thing that I was always thinking was to choose KAIST or Tokyo Tech, but I’m not going to talk about this, because it’s really devastating 😭.</p> <h2 id="final-result">Final Result</h2> <p>On <strong>January 9, 2020</strong>, the NIIED posted the final result on www.studyinkorea.go.kr. In this result, there are the names of the GKS 2020 scholars along with their Korean Language Institute (KLI), their degree university, and their college major. Because I don’t know any Korean, I have to learn Korean first at Dongseo University before studying at KAIST, even though the main language at KAIST is English.</p> <p>Finally, on <strong>January 15, 2020</strong>, the NIIED sent the Letter of Invitation via email. This letter is not only amazing because you need it to study in Korea for free but it’s also kind of challenging to get. Here’s my Letter of Invitation:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gks-und-2020-055_2_page-0001?-480.webp 480w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gks-und-2020-055_2_page-0001?-800.webp 800w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gks-und-2020-055_2_page-0001?-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gks-und-2020-055_2_page-0001.jpg?" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1> <p>That’s my journey to get the GKS 2020. It was a long and winding road, but I’m grateful for the experience. I hope my story can inspire and motivate you to apply for this scholarship. If you have any questions, feel free to ask me. I’ll be more than happy to help you. Good luck!!</p> <p><strong>-written on March 28, 2020-</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="slice of life"/><category term="scholarship"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[First and foremost, I’m not entirely sure what to write here because many people have already shared their experiences of receiving this scholarship. Nevertheless, here’s my story.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scholarship Application Story: MEXT/Monbukagakusho – Global Scientists and Engineers Program (GSEP) Tokyo Institute of Technology, Japan 🇯🇵</title><link href="https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/gsep/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scholarship Application Story: MEXT/Monbukagakusho – Global Scientists and Engineers Program (GSEP) Tokyo Institute of Technology, Japan 🇯🇵"/><published>2023-07-01T00:19:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-01T00:19:00+00:00</updated><id>https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/gsep</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/gsep/"><![CDATA[<p>I had been dreaming of studying abroad in Japan since I was in 12th grade. At that time, I already knew about some of the fully-funded scholarships in Japan such as Monbukagakusho a.k.a MEXT Scholarship via Embassy track, Mitsui Bussan Scholarship Program, and Monbukagakusho (from now on: Monbusho) via university like in Tohoku University, Tokyo Institute of Technology/Tokodai/Tokyo Tech, Kyushu University, etc. Unfortunately, in the second semester of my senior year of high school, I could only apply for the Mitsui Bussan Scholarship Program, and I didn’t even pass the document screening for that program. I didn’t apply to Monbusho via the embassy because my national exam score’s average was not good enough for the Gakubu (S1) program. I could have applied for the Kosen/Senshu Program which is equivalent to a D3/D2 program in Indonesia, but that’s not what I wanted. I also couldn’t apply for Monbusho via university because I didn’t have any English proficiency tests like TOEFL iBT or IELTS because the tests are so expensive.</p> <p>In short, I took a gap year in 2017 so that I could get money for an English proficiency test and I could apply to one of the top universities in Japan which is Tokyo Institute of Technology/Tokodai through their program called Global Scientists and Engineers Program (GSEP). In February 2018, I already had a TOEFL iBT score and I was ready to apply for the GSEP Tokodai and even in May 2018, I was starting to write the essay based on the previous year’s guidelines. Then the official guideline was released in July 2018 (if I’m not mistaken) and there’s a new rule that we need to pay for the application fee and it cost 17,000 JPY. At that time I couldn’t afford it so I didn’t apply for the program again for the second time. Finally, in 2019, I was really frustrated because I really wanted to go to college therefore I was determined to look for money and apply for the GSEP. Then the miracle came, one of my seniors, Kak Hasfi, who I never met in real life called me on the phone, then I shared all of my stories with him, and he offered me to pay my application fee for this GSEP on condition that if I pass the program and get the scholarship, I don’t need to repay him, but on the other hand, if I fail, I need to pay the application fee back to him; and at that time obviously I said yes to him and decided to use my own money to take the SAT Subject test on June 2019. Thank you very much Kak Hasfi for making this story happen haha.</p> <h2 id="so-what-is-the-global-scientists-and-engineers-program-gsep">So what is the Global Scientists and Engineers Program (GSEP)?</h2> <p><img src="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gsep.jpg" alt="Image"/></p> <p>I’m actually not going to explain about this program deeply, but in a nutshell, this is the first English-taught undergraduate program at Tokodai, and if you are admitted, you’re going to study under the Department of Transdisciplinary Science and Engineering and after finishing the program you’ll get a Bachelors of Engineering (B.Eng) from Tokyo Tech. The cool thing about this program is you don’t need to limit yourself to just learning one discipline, instead, you’ll learn various kinds of sciences and engineering subjects so you’ll be able to solve many real-life complex problems in this world. You can be divergent! For a more detailed explanation, please check this website: <a href="http://www.tse.ens.titech.ac.jp/~gsep/">GSEP</a></p> <h2 id="preliminary-screening">Preliminary Screening</h2> <p>The first screening is, of course, document screening. By the way, in GSEP 2020, only the 8 best applicants WORLDWIDE will get the MEXT Scholarship, so at that time I didn’t hope too much because this program is really competitive. So what are the documents needed for this program? I’m not going to mention it here because you can find the full application guide on this website: <a href="https://www.titech.ac.jp/english/graduate_school/international/gsep/">GSEP Application Guide</a> But I just want to mention that you need to pay the application fee which is 17,000 JPY + 500 JPY for admin fee (at that time it was about 2,3 million IDR ), so be prepared for it, especially if you struggle because of money like me.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/90620866_531813401084455_1303042152179171328_n?w=910&amp;h=512-480.webp 480w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/90620866_531813401084455_1303042152179171328_n?w=910&amp;h=512-800.webp 800w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/90620866_531813401084455_1303042152179171328_n?w=910&amp;h=512-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/90620866_531813401084455_1303042152179171328_n.jpg?w=910&amp;h=512" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>I finished my documents in the middle of August and sent my documents to Tokyo Tech around the 20th of August 2019, because at that time the deadline was September 5, 2019. I sent it using EMS service, and from the Post Office (Kantor POS) in Cianjur, it cost around 300K-ish IDR . Then, my documents arrived at Tokyo Tech at the end of August, if I’m not mistaken it just took around 4 days for my documents to arrive in Tokyo Tech.</p> <h2 id="secondary-screening">Secondary Screening</h2> <p>The preliminary screening result came out. It was in the early morning on  September 27, 2019.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gsep-email-1?w=1032&amp;h=472-480.webp 480w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gsep-email-1?w=1032&amp;h=472-800.webp 800w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gsep-email-1?w=1032&amp;h=472-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gsep-email-1.png?w=1032&amp;h=472" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>I think the secondary screening is the most important part of the selection because it consists of the academic test (high school level math, physics, and chemistry) and interview. Because I have forgotten most of HS’s science materials, so I’d been starting learning it again since May 2019. I used A-Level books for those subjects as well as watching youtube videos regarding the materials. To be honest, I was so clueless, because I actually didn’t know what I need to learn since the GSEP admission team never posted the past papers of the previous test. But I highly recommend you learn from the A-Level curriculum because the Indonesian high school curriculum is not enough (but I don’t know about our HS curriculum now). The secondary screening was held at Sampoerna University, Jakarta on Saturday, October 12, 2019.</p> <p><img src="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/whatsapp-image-2020-03-22-at-3.47.16-pm.jpeg?w=388&amp;h=560" alt="Image"/></p> <p>During the secondary screening, I felt inferior because most of the other students were already accepted in top universities in Indonesia, including one that rejected me. And the academic test was really difficult for me; the thing that I thought at that time was how can I fill the paper as logically as possible so I didn’t leave it blank. I made a portfolio that I made before and brought it to the interview. The interview wasn’t really smooth too, so after the process, I was 100% sure that I would be rejected haha. But the most important things for me were: first, I’ve done my best, and second, I got new friends. After the screening, my friends picked me up and drove me back to my house from Jakarta to Cianjur. Thanks to Sandi, Kani, and Fahad!</p> <h2 id="the-results">The Results</h2> <p>As I told you before, I was very sure that I wouldn’t get in and that’s why I applied for another scholarship program too, GKS Korea (former: KGSP), which maybe I’ll make a post about it later. I applied to GKS to enhance my chance to study abroad with a fully-funded scholarship. The GSEP result came out on November 20, 2019, approximately 1.5 months after the secondary screening. Unfortunately, from November 20, the applicants still had to wait since the results were sent by mail, not online. And on November 22, I already got an announcement that I passed the second screening process of the GKS program and I had to do a medical check-up to continue the process. On November 27, one of the applicants from Indonesia got his results, and he didn’t get in. It made me very sure that it’s impossible for me to get into this program even to be one of 8 best applicants who will get the MEXT Scholarship, that’s why on November 28 I decided to continue my medical check-up for GKS program.</p> <p>On the afternoon of November 28, after I finished my medical check-up and it cost me a lot, I checked the tracking number of my GSEP results and it said it’s already in Cianjur. From the hospital, I directly went to the post office with the hope that I could know my results as soon as possible, but then, they said that the results package was already sent to my home. On the way home, my sister texted me that there’s a package for me. My heart was beating so fast lol, I felt like I already knew that I would fail and if I didn’t get it I would be OK because I also passed the 2nd screening of GKS but still, you know what I’m saying right?</p> <p>Then, I arrived at home. My sister who knew that I applied to this program asked me to open the results ASAP. I wasn’t ready at all, and I was planning to open it at night, making a college results reaction video like what the students in the US do haha, but yeah, I opened it directly after I came home and my sister recorded it. I thought no matter when I’ll open it, the result would be still the same.</p> <p>And… This is what I got:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gsep-2?w=300&amp;h=&amp;zoom=2-480.webp 480w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gsep-2?w=300&amp;h=&amp;zoom=2-800.webp 800w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gsep-2?w=300&amp;h=&amp;zoom=2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/gsep-2.jpg?w=300&amp;h=&amp;zoom=2" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/important-notice?w=300&amp;h=&amp;zoom=2-480.webp 480w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/important-notice?w=300&amp;h=&amp;zoom=2-800.webp 800w,https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/important-notice?w=300&amp;h=&amp;zoom=2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="https://taufikmuhamady.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/important-notice.jpg?w=300&amp;h=&amp;zoom=2" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The GSEP admission and MEXT scholarship results. </div> <p>I GOT IN and I also got the scholarship! I was speechless, excited, tired because I just arrived. Every feeling is mixed and my sister was still recording it. I JUST COULDN’T BELIEVE IT!!</p> <p>But this was just the beginning of a sweet-sour dilemma that I was going to face. I also want to say thank you very much to Kak Ryza who helped me a lot during the application process, you guys can also read his story on his blog: <a href="https://adiksidiksi.wordpress.com/">Adiksidiksi</a>, but please don’t ask him too much haha. And thank you so much for everyone who helped me a lot through the process, I am sorry I can’t mention you guys’ names here but thank you~</p> <p>If you guys have a question regarding this program, you can ask me in the comment section so other people who read this post will also know your questions but please read and try to understand the guidelines first because everything is on there. You also can ask me through my social media account but I still highly recommend you ask your questions here. Thanks for reading this post and good luck with your application!</p> <p><strong>-written on March 22, 2020-</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="slice of life"/><category term="scholarship"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I had been dreaming of studying abroad in Japan since I was in 12th grade. At that time, I already knew about some of the fully-funded scholarships in Japan such as Monbukagakusho a.k.a MEXT Scholarship via Embassy track, Mitsui Bussan Scholarship Program, and Monbukagakusho (from now on: Monbusho) via university like in Tohoku University, Tokyo Institute of Technology/Tokodai/Tokyo Tech, Kyushu University, etc. Unfortunately, in the second semester of my senior year of high school, I could only apply for the Mitsui Bussan Scholarship Program, and I didn’t even pass the document screening for that program. I didn’t apply to Monbusho via the embassy because my national exam score’s average was not good enough for the Gakubu (S1) program. I could have applied for the Kosen/Senshu Program which is equivalent to a D3/D2 program in Indonesia, but that’s not what I wanted. I also couldn’t apply for Monbusho via university because I didn’t have any English proficiency tests like TOEFL iBT or IELTS because the tests are so expensive.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The School of Life: Gap Years</title><link href="https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/gap-year/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The School of Life: Gap Years"/><published>2023-06-30T23:55:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-30T23:55:00+00:00</updated><id>https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/gap-year</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/gap-year/"><![CDATA[<p>First and foremost, you’ll notice that there’s an ‘s’ in my title, “Gap Years”. Yes! If you see the picture that I included in this post, I felt like that person who is flying between high school and college for about 2 – 3 years. Was it terrible? It actually was! Do I regret it? Hmm, no, I don’t. In Indonesia, many students don’t want to take and avoid gap year(s) because it’s somewhat embarrassing. So after graduating from high school, people start asking questions like which campus you got into, what’s your major, etc., which were really annoying to me, and yeah, I couldn’t answer those questions. Another thing that I hated at that time was the reality that I would be left behind by my peers because they were going to college and I was still nothing. But yeah, that was a small-minded version of me back in 2017. But now, I am really grateful that I had to experience gap years in my life because it taught me a lot of important things which I can’t find in any formal educational institution. Those things were dealing with failures and cyber-bullying, making decisions, traveling, meeting new people, learning from mistakes, knowing how hard it is to make money, and many more.</p> <h2 id="what-did-i-do-during-gap-years">What did I do during gap years?</h2> <p>I think I spent most of my gap years hunting scholarships, traveling, and doing stupid things, LOL. During this period, I finally realized my dream to go abroad, and my first country was Cambodia – I was selected to be one of the Indonesia representatives for the YSEALI STEM Education Workshop 2018. After that event, I felt like it was easier for me to go abroad, which I never expected in my life before. I went to Singapore, Malaysia, China, Japan, and now I am living in South Korea. I also got my first job at Ruangguru as a tutor, and I am really grateful for it. Last but not least, I finally got into several universities in many countries such as the Netherlands, Turkey, Cyprus, China, Japan, and South Korea. One thing that I still can’t believe is that I successfully got all of the fully-funded scholarships from the governments of the three East Asian countries to pursue an undergraduate degree. For me, it was like a miracle because I never thought about it before, I was even rejected by my dream university in Indonesia! But yeah, it actually happened, and I am thinking of making separate posts about this.</p> <h2 id="so-whats-the-point-do-i-recommend-you-to-take-gap-years">So what’s the point? Do I recommend you to take gap years?</h2> <p>I DO recommend taking gap year(s) if you’re the kind of person who likes challenges, wants to experience something new, and already knows what you’re going to do during gap year(s), especially to achieve your goals and dreams. But I want to remind you that gap year(s) is not an easy thing, and that’s why you also have to consider its consequences; I bet you’re going to hate gap year(s) at first but you’ll be grateful for it at the end. If you’ve already decided to take gap year(s), congratulations! Because you guys are brave to be different, to take risks, and to do what you want to do in your life.</p> <p>The last thing I want to say is please don’t give a damn about what people say if it makes you feel small, unmotivated, or insecure because your life is yours, and you are the one who’s going to experience everything</p> <p>that happens in your life, not other people. Anyways, good luck to all of the readers for all of the decisions that you guys have made. I hope you guys can achieve all of your goals and dreams.</p> <p>200309<br/> Busan, South Korea. In the middle of the COVID-19 epidemic which I hope will be over as soon as possible~</p> <p><strong>-written on March 8, 2020-</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="slice of life"/><category term="gap year"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[First and foremost, you’ll notice that there’s an ‘s’ in my title, “Gap Years”. Yes! If you see the picture that I included in this post, I felt like that person who is flying between high school and college for about 2 – 3 years. Was it terrible? It actually was! Do I regret it? Hmm, no, I don’t. In Indonesia, many students don’t want to take and avoid gap year(s) because it’s somewhat embarrassing. So after graduating from high school, people start asking questions like which campus you got into, what’s your major, etc., which were really annoying to me, and yeah, I couldn’t answer those questions. Another thing that I hated at that time was the reality that I would be left behind by my peers because they were going to college and I was still nothing. But yeah, that was a small-minded version of me back in 2017. But now, I am really grateful that I had to experience gap years in my life because it taught me a lot of important things which I can’t find in any formal educational institution. Those things were dealing with failures and cyber-bullying, making decisions, traveling, meeting new people, learning from mistakes, knowing how hard it is to make money, and many more.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Beginning: Abroad</title><link href="https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/the-beginning-abroad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Beginning: Abroad"/><published>2023-06-30T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-30T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/the-beginning-abroad</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/the-beginning-abroad/"><![CDATA[<p>Ever since high school, I’ve been dreaming of going abroad and even traveling the world. Why? I don’t know, I just thought it was cool. But then I realized that going overseas meant I could experience something different, meet new people, and understand other people’s cultures. Indeed, those things are fascinating. As a broke student (I’m still broke now), it seemed impossible to realize that dream, so I had to find a way to go abroad without burning a hole in my wallet.</p> <p>The first idea that came to my mind was joining a science Olympiad competition with the expectation that I could represent my country at the international science Olympiad competition. (You can notice that it’s totally the wrong intention LOL, and I guess you will know what happened next).</p> <p>In short, I failed in that science Olympiad competition; I just made it to the provincial level. By the way, I chose astronomy as my subject, for no particular reason. At that time, I didn’t realize how ill-suited I was for the science Olympiad thing, but yeah, at least I learned a little bit about constellations, planets, and dark matter, haha. The first plan didn’t work, so I had to find another way to go abroad – by continuing my higher education in another country with a full scholarship.</p> <p>During my senior year, I started to research fully-funded scholarships to pursue a bachelor’s degree abroad. I found a lot of information regarding scholarships in various countries such as Turkey, Japan, China, South Korea, India, Russia, Malaysia, Brunei, the Netherlands, Singapore, etc. (I already made a post about this, but it’s in Bahasa Indonesia). I really wanted to apply to every single scholarship program out there, but unfortunately, I didn’t have a lot of money to take the English proficiency exam and the standardized test required by most of the scholarship programs. I didn’t want to burden my parents with that because those tests are incredibly expensive! In the end, during my senior year, I could only apply to one scholarship program in Turkey called Turkiye Burslari because it didn’t require me to have the tests that I mentioned before, so it’s the simplest scholarship program to apply.</p> <p><strong>Plot twist:</strong> After graduating from high school, I got a lot of information about exchange programs like AFS from Binabud and how to continue your high school abroad through the UWC program. I really regret not knowing about those programs earlier. I wish I knew about it, so I could dedicate myself to those programs instead of spending my time on the Olympiad stuff LOL. Trust me! Exchange programs and conferences are ‘easier’ to get rather than a medal in a science Olympiad, especially for a person like me, haha. So for you guys who are still in high school, please use your time wisely so you won’t regret your high school life.</p> <p>This is just the beginning. This story led me to such a roller coaster journey that I am going to tell next. I hope you guys enjoy my story, and thank you for reading it. See you~</p> <p><strong>-written on November 17, 2019-</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="slice of life"/><category term="scholarship"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ever since high school, I’ve been dreaming of going abroad and even traveling the world. Why? I don’t know, I just thought it was cool. But then I realized that going overseas meant I could experience something different, meet new people, and understand other people’s cultures. Indeed, those things are fascinating. As a broke student (I’m still broke now), it seemed impossible to realize that dream, so I had to find a way to go abroad without burning a hole in my wallet.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beasiswa S1 Dunia!</title><link href="https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/beasiswa-s1-dunia/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beasiswa S1 Dunia!"/><published>2023-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/beasiswa-s1-dunia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/beasiswa-s1-dunia/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Disclaimer: I wrote it long time ago in 2017, it’s gonna be a bit cringe but I just wanna transfer it here</strong></p> <p>Melanjutkan pendidikan ke Perguruan Tinggi memang dirasa penting, terutama bagi mereka lulusan SMA. Di Indonesia sendiri ada beberapa jalur masuk perguruan tinggi, yaitu SNMPTN, SBMPTN, dan mungkin ujian mandiri yang diselenggarakan oleh beberapa universitas saja. Namun jika kita meng-explore lebih, banyak lho beasiswa-beasiswa untuk melanjutkan pendidikan S1 (undergraduate) di luar negeri, dan yang lebih pentingnya lagi ini BEASISWA ! Kalian gak harus ngebebanin orang tua kalian dalam biaya perkuliahan, atau paling tidak meminimalisir biaya perkuliahan yang harus orang tua bayar. Yuk langsung saja kita bahas satu persatu beasiswa-beasiswa S1 dunia yang sudah saya ringkas.</p> <p><strong>1. Türkiye Bursları</strong></p> <p>Beasiswa ini diselenggarakan oleh Yurtdışı Türkler ve Akraba Topluluklar Başkanlığı (YTB) atau Repbulic of Turkiye Prime Ministry Presidency Turks Aboard and Related Communities semacam Kementrian Luar Negerinya Turki gitu. Beasiswa ini bersifat fully funded yang menanggung biaya pendidikan, biaya hidup, tempat tinggal jika tinggal di asrama pemerintah, tiket pesawat pada saat keberangkatan dan pada saat nanti lulus dan pulang ke negeri asalnya, dan biaya belajar bahasa Turki selama setahun.</p> <p>Seleksi beasiswa YTB ini terdiri dari dua tahap, yaitu tahap seleksi berkas dan tahap interview. Untuk seleksi berkas, dokumen yang dibutuhkan seperti kartu identitas (Paspor/KTP/KK/Akta kelahiran), transkrip nilai SMA, Ijazah (kalau sudah ada), surat rekomendasi, dan sertifikat, oh iya diusahakan semua dokumennya ditranslate kedalam bahasa Inggris ya, kecuali sertifikat dan kartu identitas.</p> <p>Setelah lolos tahap seleksi berkas ini, maka akan lanjut ke tahap interview yang biasanya lokasinya di Kedubes Turki di Jakarta, tapi untuk tahun 2017 ini lokasinya di JS Luwangsa Hotel Jakarta. Kemudian setelah interview, kita akan menunggu selama beberapa bulan sampai pengumuman akhir diumumkan.</p> <p>Oh iya, kebetulan sekarang ini saya sedang dalam proses seleksi beasiswa ini, Alhamdulillah sekarang sedang menunggu pengumuman akhirnya setelah kemarin tanggal 9 Mei 2017 proses interview dilaksanakan. Mohon doanya ya teman-teman agar saya dapat lolos beasiswa ini. InsyaAllah saya akan menulis tentang beasiswa ini lebih lengkap pada postingan berikutnya.</p> <p><strong>2. Monbukagakusho</strong></p> <p>Yup, dari namanya kita bisa menebak beasiswa ini diberikan oleh pemerintah Jepang. Beasiswa ini juga bersifat fully funded, fasilitas yang diberikan hampir sama dengan beasiswa Turki, tapi tidak termasuk asrama cmiiw. Sebelum masuk univ yang dituju, penerima beasiswa ini pun akan belajar bahasa Jepang dulu selama setahun. Ada syarat khusus untuk mendaftar beasiswa ini, jika kalian ingin mendaftar untuk program S1, rata-rata nilai UN kalian minimal 8,4, dan jika ingin mendaftar program D3 atau D2, rata-rata nilai UN kalian minimal 8,0. Jujur saja saya tidak jadi mendaftar beasiswa ini karena saya ingin mendaftar program S1 tapi rata-rata nilai UN saya kurang dari 8,4 walaupun kurang 0,sekian.</p> <p>Untuk seleksinya pertama yang pasti seleksi berkas, kemudian setelah lolos seleksi berkas akan ada tes tertulis, dan jika lolos tes tertulis akan ada seleksi interview. Ganbatteee! hehe</p> <p><strong>3. Mitsui Bussan</strong></p> <p>Mitsui Bussan ini adalah beasiswa bagi kalian yang ingin melanjutkan pendidikan kalian ke Jepang yang diselenggarakan oleh Mitsui &amp; Co., Ltd. Beasiswa ini juga fully funded, mencakup biaya pendidikan, tiket pesawat ke Jepang, akomodasi, dll. Tapi jujur saja, persaingan untuk memperbutkan beasiswa ini sangat-sangat ketat, karena pada akhirnya hanya akan menyisakan DUA pendaftar saja yang akan dinobatkan sebagai Awardee Mitsui Bussan Scholarship ini.</p> <p>Untuk seleksinya sendiri dimulai dari seleksi berkas, tes tulis yang terdiri dari Matematika dan Bahasa Inggris, tes psikologi dan kesehatan, dan terakhir seleksi interview. Saya sempat mendaftar beasiswa ini, akan tetapi karena mungkin saya kurang begitu mempersiapkan untuk beasiswa ini, saya tidak lolos walaupun hanya seleksi berkas.</p> <p><strong>4. Chinese Government Scholarship</strong></p> <p>Beasiswa pemerintah China ini bersifat fully funded, mencakup biaya kuliah, tempat tinggal, buku, asuransi kesehatan, dan tentunya uang saku, tapi tanpa tiket pesawat. Oh iya kalau saya tidak salah, beasiswa ini hanya ada seleksi berkas saja lho, tanpa seleksi interview, kecuali kalau ada universitas yang mengharuskan interview.</p> <p><strong>5. Korean Government Scholarship Program (KGSP)</strong></p> <p>Beasiswa ini cocok banget buat kalian yang pengen banget kuliah di Korea Selatan. Beasiswa ini juga bersifat fully funded mencakup biaya pendidikan, tunjangan kedatangan dan kepulangan, biaya hidup, tiket pesawat, dll. At the end I got this scholarship xD</p> <p>Selain beasiswa-beasiswa di atas yang sudah saya sebutkan, masih banyak lagi beasiswa-beasiswa untuk undergraduate program seperti Beasiswa Pemerintah Russia, Beasiswa Pemerintah Brunei Darussalam, Beasiswa Pemerintah Republik Ceko, Beasiswa Pemerintah Hungaria, dan beasiswa yang diselenggarakan oleh beberapa universitas tertentu. Namun saya tidak dapat menjelaskannya satu persatu, karena selain banyak sekali, saya pun tidak daftar semua program beasiswa tersebut. Jika kalian tertarik, silakan cari informasinya sendiri ya, jangan jadi pejuang malas hehe.</p> <p>Jadi untuk teman-teman yang membaca tulisan ini saya berpesan jangan takut untuk melanjutkan pendidikan kalian! Sekarang ini sudah banyak beasiswa-beasiswa yang bertebaran, apalagi kita juga berkesempatan untuk belajar di negeri orang, gratis pula. Sekarang tinggal kalian yang menentukan, berani untuk mencoba atau diam dan membuang kesempatan yang kalian punya? Intinya jangan takut untuk mencoba dan jangan takut untuk bermimpi! Semangaaatt!!</p> <blockquote> <p>It’s big world out there, it would be a shame not to experience it.</p> </blockquote> <p><strong>-written on June 6, 2017-</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="slice of life"/><category term="scholarship"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Disclaimer: I wrote it long time ago in 2017, it’s gonna be a bit cringe but I just wanna transfer it here]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hello World 👋</title><link href="https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/helloworld/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello World 👋"/><published>2023-06-26T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-26T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/helloworld</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://taufik-my.github.io/blog/2023/helloworld/"><![CDATA[<p>Beep boop….</p> <p>Hello, world! Taufik’s here, an alien 👽 trying to make a contact with you! Finally I have a way to do that through this personal website, very excited!</p> <p>This first posting is to test whether it works or not haha. I will try to write my experiences and projects in this site. Hopefully you will enjoy reading the posts here as I do for writing it.</p> <p>Oh, you also can contact me through my social medias that you can find on the left-bottom corner of this site. Don’t hesitate to contact me ^^</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">See you later!</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>-Taufik-</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Beep boop….]]></summary></entry></feed>